Edward Abbey papers, 1947-1990
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collection
Papers of Edward Abbey, 1947-1990
MS 271
Abbey, Edward.
Papers, 1947-1990, of Edward Abbey, author. Contains biographical materials, correspondence, journals, notebooks, speeches, manuscripts, articles, audiotapes, videotapes, and supplemental materials documenting his life and career.
12.1 feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collection University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Edward Abbey was born on 29 January 1927 in Home, Pennsylvania, the eldest son of five children born to Mildred and Paul Abbey. At seventeen, he first hitchhiked across the West on a three month journey. From 1945 to 1946, he served in the U.S. Army in Alabama and Italy.
In 1948, while attending the University of New Mexico, Abbey began work on his first novel, Jonathan Troy (1956). In 1951, he earned a BA in English and Philosophy from that university, and published an article, "Some Implications of Anarchy." That same year Abbey received a Fullbright Fellowship to Edinburgh University. In the early 1950s, he worked as a social welfare case worker in New Jersey and New York.
In 1956, he received a MA in Philosophy from the University of New Mexico; his graduate thesis was titled "Anarchism and the Morality of Violence." The following year, he received a Writing Fellowship at Stanford University.
Abbey worked part-time as a park ranger and fire lookout in the national parks and forests of the southwestern United States. He would continue this work until the 1970s. With the publication of The Monkey Wrench Gang, he was able to devote his time more fully to writing. Abbey gave public readings and presentations at many American colleges and universities, and for the environmental causes and groups he supported. In 1974, he received a Guggenheim Fellowship. During this time, Abbey was "Writer in Residence" at the University of Utah and, later, at the University of Arizona. He taught creative writing at the latter from 1981 onwards, and became a full professor there in 1988.
Abbey died 14 March 1989 in Tucson Arizona at the age of 62. Married five times, he was survived by his wife, Clarke Cartwright Abbey, and his five children.
His selected major novels include: The Brave Cowboy (1956), Fire on the Mountain (1962), Black Sun (1971), The Monkey Wrench Gang (1975), Good News (1980), The Fool's Progress (1988), and Hayduke Lives! (1990). His essays and observations are compiled in Desert Solitaire (1968), The Journey Home (1977), Abbey's Road (1979), Desert Images (1981), One Life at a Time, Please (1987), and Vox Clamantis in Deserto (1989). He produced several travel books Appalachian Wilderness (1970), Slickrock (1971), Cactus Country (1972), and The Hidden Canyon (1978). He contributed to divers college anthologies, and wrote numerous articles and reviews for national and regional publications.
Organization
This collection is organized into 7 series.
Series 1: Biographical Materials, 1947-1989
Series 2: Correspondence, 1966-1989
Series 3: Journals, 1951-1989
Series 4: Notebooks and Speeches, 1951-1988
Series 5: Works, 1951-1990
Series 6: Audio-visual Materials, 1959-1989
Series 7: Supplemental Materials, 1974-1988
Scope and Content Note
The bulk of the collection best documents Abbey's writings and activities during the last two decades of his life, 1969 to 1989. Over half of the collection consist of drafts of his novels, essays, articles, and other works. There are no drafts for his earlier novels, Jonathan Troy, The Brave Cowboy, and Fire on the Mountain, nor for Appalachian Wilderness and The Hidden Canyon.
His personal life and professional career are summarily described in the Biographical Materials. Interviews and recordings of Abbey are available in that series, and in the Audio-visual series. Articles about him as a writer and defender of the environment are located in the Works series.
His frank Outgoing Correspondence and Journals provide a thorough account of his life and thoughts. Especially in the Journals, he chronicles the progress or regression of his writings; his love for family, friends, colleagues, and classical music; his thoughts on contemporary society; notes for his fictional characters; snippets of conversations overheard, jokes told, or gossip exchanged; his observations on daily life and trips taken; rough drafts of letters to be sent to editors or friends; and a other notes worth noting.
See the Series Descriptions below for a fuller narrative of the contents of each.
Abbey, Edward, 1927- -- Archives.; Dillard, Annie -- Correspondence.; Eastlake, William -- Correspondence.; Harrington, Alan, 1919- -- Correspondence.; Hoagland, Ted -- Correspondence.; Lopez, Barry Holstun, 1945- -- Correspondence.; Nichols, John Treadwell, 1940- -- Correspondence.; Authors, American -- 20th century -- Archives.; Civil disobedience.; Environmental literature -- Archival resources.; Conservation of natural resources -- Citizen participation.; Deserts in literature.; West (U.S.) -- In literature -- Archival resources.; Arizona -- Fiction.; Southwest, New -- Description and travel.
Container List
- Series 1: Biographical Information, 1947-1989
  Contains personal data relating to his family and career, including University of Arizona teaching files, memorials and tributes written after his death, interviews with Abbey appearing in various publications such as Bloomsbury Review, and The Mother Earth News [see also Audio-visual Materials for additional untranscribed interviews]; and a Federal Bureau of Investigation file on him obtained under the Freedom of Information Act.
  - Certificates, resumes, vita, family tree, 1947-1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - University of Arizona teaching file, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Memorials and tributes, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Interviews, 1969-1988 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - F.B.I. file, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series 2: Correspondence, 1966-1989
  Family correspondents include his children Aaron, Joshua, and Susie; his siblings John, Nancy, and Bill Abbey; one of his wives, Judy Abbey; and a larger set from his parents Mildred and Paul Abbey.
  Incoming and outgoing folders contain letters to and from Abbey chiefly regarding his writing. Selected correspondents include: Horace Albright; Carroll Ballard; Wendell Berry; Don Congdon (literary agent); Annie Dillard; William Eastlake; Lawrence Ferlinghetti; Alan Harrington; Ted Hoagland; Richard Lamm; Jack Loeffler; Barry Lopez; John Macrae (publisher and editor); John G. Mitchell; John Nichols; Doug Peacock; Robert Redford; Norman Sanders; Pete Seeger; and Gary Snyder. Also includes unsorted "letters to the editor" about Abbey and his writings, and "fan" mail.
  - Series 2.1: Family Correspondence, 1966-1988
    - Children, 1976-1988 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Siblings, 1967-1987 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Parents: Mildred and Paul Abbey, 1966-1988 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
    - Abbey, Judy, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 2.2: Incoming Correspondence, 1967-1989
    - Incoming, A-Z, 1967-1989 (Box 2, Folder 4-12)
    - Ballard, Carroll (Monkey Wrench Gang Screenplay), 1985-1987 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Congdon, Don (Literary Agent), 1970-1986 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Reader comments on articles, 1970-1980s (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Fan mail, 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Subseries 2.3: Outgoing Correspondence, 1969-1989
    - Outgoing, 1967-1989 (Box 3, Folder 5-20)
- Series 3: Journals, 1951-1989
  Contains mostly handwritten accounts of his daily activities and reflections on his personal relationships and professional accomplishments, especially in his journals numbered four through twenty accounting for the years 1951-89 [journals one through three are missing]. Also includes smaller chronicles on a hospital stay, various trips, and other activities. Abbey recorded additional diaries and trips in his Notebooks in the following series.
  - Journals 4-12, 1951-1966 (Box 4, Folder 1-9)
  - Journals 13-20, 1966-1989 (Box 5, Folder 1-8)
  - A Hospital Journal, no date (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Lookout's Logbook, Glacier National Park, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Cabeza Prieta walks, 1980 [?], 1984 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Trip: Kansas to Home, PA., 1986; Earth First! Rally, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Trip: Grand Gulch; Notes on drag-line machine, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Series 4: Notebooks and Speeches, 1951-1988
  Chiefly notebooks with handwritten notes pertaining to ideas, characters, dialogue, and revision of his novels, articles and speeches. Also contains typescripts of speeches, some with corrections and additions, given by Abbey over two decades, from 1968 to 1988.Additional speeches are found in the Audio visual Materials.
  - The Brave Cowboy, no date (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - The Good Life, no date (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Great books of anarchism; Black Sun, ca. 1951 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Untitled, ca. 1962-1970 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Speeches, no dates (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Speeches, 1968-1975 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Speeches, 1976-1988 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Speeches/Notes: Boro Council Minutes, Seneca Evening Gazette, Desert Solitaire, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Speeches/Notes: Monkey Wrench Gang, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Speeches/Notes, 1972- ca.1980s (Box 8, Folder 1-6)
  - Speeches/Notes: Lake Foul (Powell) trip, teaching, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Speeches/Notes: Hopi runners, Oraibi trip, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Speeches/Notes: Alaska trip, teaching, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Speeches/Notes, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Speeches/Notes: Telluride, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Series 5: Works, 1951-1990
  - Subseries 5.1: Manuscripts, 1959-1990
    Arranged alphabetical by title. Contains original handwritten, typed, carbons, photocopied, and revised manuscripts mostly of Abbey's published novels and essays. Some titles lack complete versions of text. Many of the drafts were undated, and many contained handwritten corrections in ink and pencil by the author. When available, descriptive notes for the folder headings were copied from envelopes containing the manuscripts. Some manuscripts for earlier titles are not present.
    - Abbey's Road (fragment, chapter 4), n.d. (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - "Anarchism and the Morality of Violence," (M.A. thesis), 1959 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Beyond the Wall typescript with corrections, no date (Box 9, Folder 3-4)
    - Beyond the Wall draft, fragment with corrections, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Beyond the Wall galley proof with corrections, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Black Sun original manuscript, no date (Box 9, Folder 7-9)
    - Black Sun revised manuscript, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
    - Cactus Country 1st draft, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Cactus Country 2nd draft, no date (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - City of Dreadful Night original manuscript, no date (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - City of Dreadful Night original manuscript, no date (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
    - Desert Images, 1979 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Desert Music, 1976 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Desert Solitaire original manuscript, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 5-6)
    - Desert Solitaire revised manuscript, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 7-8)
    - Down the River, 1980 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Good News corrected manuscript, no date (Box 12, Folder 1-2)
    - Good News revised carbon, 1980 (Box 12, Folder 3-4)
    - Good News master, 1st pass, 1980 (Box 12, Folder 5-6)
    - Fool's Progress outlines, no date (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Fool's Progress draft handwritten, no date (Box 13, Folder 2-6)
    - Fool's Progress original typescript with corrections, no date (Box 14, Folder 1-6)
    - Fool's Progress original typescript with corrections, no date (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Fool's Progress, draft typescript with corrections, no date (Box 15, Folder 2-5)
    - Fool's Progress, draft typescript with corrections, no date (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Fool's Progress proof with corrections, 1988 (Box 16, Folder 2-6)
    - Fool's Progress, addition to Avon edition, 1990 (Box 16, Folder 7-8)
    - Good Life outline, notes, no date (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Good Life draft with corrections, no date (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Hayduke Lives! outline, notes, no date (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Hayduke Lives! original typescript, 1988 (Box 17, Folder 4-7)
    - Hayduke Lives! carbons, 1988 (Box 18, Folder 1-2)
    - Hayduke Lives! photocopy with editing by Clarke, no date (Box 18, Folder 3-5)
    - Hayduke Lives! retyped by Little, Brown, 1989 (Box 18, Folder 6-7)
    - Journey Home draft corrected, 1976 (Box 19, Folder 1-2)
    - Monkey Wrench Gang 1st draft typescript with corrections, no date (Box 19, Folder 3-6)
    - Monkey Wrench Gang 1st draft typescript with corrections, no date (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Monkey Wrench Gang draft typescript with corrections, 1975 (Box 20, Folder 2-6)
    - Monkey Wrench Gang miscellaneous carbons, Avon ed., chapter 21, no date (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - One Life at a Time, Please original and carbons, ca. 1988 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - One Life at a Time, Please draft with corrections, 1988 (Box 21, Folder 2-5)
    - One Life at a Time, Please proofs author's and marked set, no date (Box 21, Folder 6-7)
    - One Life at a Time, Please proofs 1st revised master set, no date (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - Slickrock typescript with corrections, 1970-1971 (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - Vox Clamantis in Deserto agreement and original (photocopy) for Rydal Press, 1989 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - notes, drafts with corrections, carbons, 1989 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Subseries 5.2: Screenplays, 1969-1988
    Arranged by title. Contains typescripts, carbons, and corrections to two novels that were considered for adaptation to film. The bulk relates to The Monkey Wrench Gang, and has scripts by Abbey and others. Correspondence between Abbey and Carroll Ballard is filed in that series.
    - Black Sun 1st draft, 1969 (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Black Sun carbon, no date (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Monkey Wrench Gang notes, 1986 (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Monkey Wrench Gang scripts by Abbey and others, 1985-1988 (Box 23, Folder 4-9)
  - Subseries 5.3: Articles by Abbey, 1951-1990
    Arranged chronologically. Contains typescripts, tearsheets and photocopies of essays and articles published in a wide variety of journals, newspapers, and similar publications. The predominant themes of the articles are his experiences as a park ranger and river runner, and his views on the current state of culture and the environment. Many of his "letters to the editors" are found in the Correspondence series; outlines and notes to some articles may be found in the Journal and Notebook series.
    - Undated, 1951-1979 (Box 24, Folder 1-10)
    - 1980-1990 (Box 25, Folder 1-3)
  - Subseries 5.4: Book Reviews by Abbey, 1969-1988
    - 1969-1988 (Box 25, Folder 4-5)
  - Subseries 5.5: Plays, no date
    - "Best of the West: a morality in one short act," no date (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - Subseries 5.6: Poems, 1965-1980s
    - 1965-1980s (Box 25, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 5.7: Articles about Abbey, 1964-1990
    - 1964-1990 (Box 25, Folder 8-10)
  - Subseries 5.8: Reviews of Abbey's Works, 1954-1990
    - Abbey's Road, 1979 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - Beyond the Wall, 1984 (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - Brave Cowboy, 1962-1968 (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - Desert Solitaire, 1968-1988 (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - Down the River, 1982 (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - Fool's Progress, 1988-1989 (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - Good News, 1981 (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - Hayduke Lives!, 1989-1990 (Box 26, Folder 8)
    - Journey Home, 1977 (Box 26, Folder 9)
    - Monkey Wrench Gang, 1975-1976 (Box 26, Folder 10)
    - One Life at a Time, Please, 1988 (Box 26, Folder 11)
    - Vox Clamantis, 1990 (Box 26, Folder 12)
    - Miscellaneous, 1954-1988 (Box 26, Folder 13)
- Series 6: Audio-visual materials, 1959-1989
  Arranged by record type, then chronologically. Contains audio cassette tapes, video cassette tapes, microfilm, and a photograph. The captions for the titles were taken from the annotations on the containers, and not all materials were screened for verification of contents. Master copies of the tapes were made and are in Box 30.
  The tapes are chiefly interviews and speeches by or about Abbey. Of interest are tapes of a cross-country trip by Abbey from Arizona to Pennsylvania.
  The microfilm is of issues of a newspaper El Crepusculo de la Libertad (Taos, New Mexico) during Abbey's editorship; original copies are also present.
  One color photograph shows a man wearing a tee-shirt with a quote from Abbey's fictional character G.W. Hayduke on the back side. There are no portraits of Abbey in this series.
  - Subseries 6.1: Audio cassette tapes, 1976-1989
    - Interview, Channel 3, March 1976 (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - University of Denver, May 3, 1976 (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - University of Arizona, February 2, 1977 (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - Interview with Jack Loeffler, January 1, 1983 (Box 27, Folder 4-5)
    - University of Montana, April 1, 1985 (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - Road trip: Oracle, Arizona to Home, Pennsylvania, ca. 1987 (Box 27, Folder 7-9)
    - New Dimensions, October 28, 1988 (Box 27, Folder 10)
    - Earth First! Rally, Tucson, Ariz., Ed Abbey, Dave Forman, Bill Oliver, March 4, 1989 (Box 27, Folder 11)
    - Memorial for Ed Abbey, May 20, 1989 (Box 27, Folder 12)
    - Vic and Don, no date (Box 27, Folder 13-14)
  - Subseries 6.2: Microfilm, 1959-1960
    - El Crepusculo de la Libertad, October 29, 1959 to January 21, 1960 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - El Crepusculo, original copies, XI:44-49, 51-52; XII:1-4 (Box 28, Folder 2-3)
  - Subseries 6.3: Photographs
    - Hayduke tee-shirt, no date (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - Subseries 6.4: Video cassettes, 1983-1988
    - KAET (Phoenix, Ariz.): "Edward Abbey's Road," 1983 (Box 28)
    - KCET: "Wilderness Journal," 1983 (Box 28)
    - Speech: Lewis-Clark State College, March 24, 1985 (Box 28)
    - NBC Almanac (Out in the Rocks?), 1986 (Box 28)
    - "3rd Annual Archdruid Lecture Series": Sierra Club benefit, Salt Lake City, Utah, January 15, 1988 (Box 28)
    - Cracking of the Glen Canyon Damn. (Box 28)
    - "Remembering Edward Abbey," by Shawn Emery. Uses above materials, 39 minutes, 44 seconds, 1992 (Box 28)
- Series 7: Supplemental materials, 1974-1988
  Contains sundry printed and handwritten items by or about Abbey including notes; clippings on his friends, Dave Foreman, Ken Sleight, and Doug Peacock; research for Hayduke Lives!; some royalty statements; Sierra Club and Earth First! calendars, some with handwritten annotations by Abbey; and miscellaneous materials relating to Abbey from other sources added after the original accession was processed.
  - Miscellaneous, no date (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - Friends of Abbey, ca. 1988 (Box 29, Folder 2)
  - Research on Hayduke Lives!, ca. 1988 (Box 29, Folder 3)
  - Royalty statements, 1986-1988 (Box 29, Folder 4)
  - Calendars, some with notes by Abbey, 1974-1984 (Box 29, Folder 5)
  - Materials added after original processing, from other sources. (Box 29, Folder 6)
  - Masters of audio cassette tapes (14). Note: Not for researcher use, please use copies in Box 27. (Box 30)
  - Masters of video tapes (3): NBC Almanac, Wilderness Journal, Edward Abbey's Road. Note: Not for researcher use, please use copies in Box 28. (Box 30)